وَجَاءَتْ كُلُّ نَفْسٍ مَعَهَا سَائِقٌ وَشَهِيدٌ ﴿21﴾
And every soul will come, with it a driver and a witness.
لَقَدْ كُنْتَ فِي غَفْلَةٍ مِنْ هَٰذَا فَكَشَفْنَا عَنْكَ غِطَاءَكَ فَبَصَرُكَ الْيَوْمَ حَدِيدٌ ﴿22﴾
[It will be said], "You were certainly in unmindfulness of this, and We have removed from you your cover, so your sight, this Day, is sharp."
وَقَالَ قَرِينُهُ هَٰذَا مَا لَدَيَّ عَتِيدٌ ﴿23﴾ أَلْقِيَا فِي جَهَنَّمَ كُلَّ كَفَّارٍ عَنِيدٍ ﴿24﴾
And his companion, [the angel], will say, "This [record] is what is with me, prepared."  [ Allah will say], "Throw into Hell every obstinate disbeliever,
مَنَّاعٍ لِلْخَيْرِ مُعْتَدٍ مُرِيبٍ ﴿25﴾ الَّذِي جَعَلَ مَعَ اللَّهِ إِلَٰهًا آخَرَ فَأَلْقِيَاهُ فِي الْعَذَابِ الشَّدِيدِ ﴿26﴾
Preventer of good, aggressor, and doubter, who made [as equal] with Allah another deity; then throw him into the severe punishment."
قَالَ قَرِينُهُ رَبَّنَا مَا أَطْغَيْتُهُ وَلَٰكِنْ كَانَ فِي ضَلَالٍ بَعِيدٍ ﴿27﴾
His [devil] companion will say, "Our Lord, I did not make him transgress, but he [himself] was in extreme error."
قَالَ لَا تَخْتَصِمُوا لَدَيَّ وَقَدْ قَدَّمْتُ إِلَيْكُمْ بِالْوَعِيدِ ﴿28﴾
[ Allah ] will say, "Do not dispute before Me, while I had already presented to you the warning.
مَا يُبَدَّلُ الْقَوْلُ لَدَيَّ وَمَا أَنَا بِظَلَّامٍ لِلْعَبِيدِ ﴿29﴾
The word will not be changed with Me, and never will I be unjust to the servants."
يَوْمَ نَقُولُ لِجَهَنَّمَ هَلِ امْتَلَأْتِ وَتَقُولُ هَلْ مِنْ مَزِيدٍ ﴿30﴾
On the Day We will say to Hell, "Have you been filled?" and it will say, "Are there some more,"
وَلَقَدْ خَلَقْنَا الْإِنْسَانَ وَنَعْلَمُ مَا تُوَسْوِسُ بِهِ نَفْسُهُ ۖ وَنَحْنُ أَقْرَبُ إِلَيْهِ مِنْ حَبْلِ الْوَرِيدِ ﴿16﴾
And We have already created man and know what his soul whispers to him, and We are closer to him than [his] jugular vein
إِذْ يَتَلَقَّى الْمُتَلَقِّيَانِ عَنِ الْيَمِينِ وَعَنِ الشِّمَالِ قَعِيدٌ ﴿17﴾
When the two receivers receive, seated on the right and on the left.
مَا يَلْفِظُ مِنْ قَوْلٍ إِلَّا لَدَيْهِ رَقِيبٌ عَتِيدٌ ﴿18﴾
Man does not utter any word except that with him is an observer prepared [to record].
وَجَاءَتْ سَكْرَةُ الْمَوْتِ بِالْحَقِّ ۖ ذَٰلِكَ مَا كُنْتَ مِنْهُ تَحِيدُ ﴿19﴾
And the intoxication of death will bring the truth; that is what you were trying to avoid.
وَنُفِخَ فِي الصُّورِ ۚ ذَٰلِكَ يَوْمُ الْوَعِيدِ ﴿20﴾
And the Horn will be blown. That is the Day of [carrying out] the threat.
وَجَاءَتْ كُلُّ نَفْسٍ مَعَهَا سَائِقٌ وَشَهِيدٌ ﴿21﴾
And every soul will come, with it a driver and a witness.
لَقَدْ كُنْتَ فِي غَفْلَةٍ مِنْ هَٰذَا فَكَشَفْنَا عَنْكَ غِطَاءَكَ فَبَصَرُكَ الْيَوْمَ حَدِيدٌ ﴿22﴾
[It will be said], "You were certainly in unmindfulness of this, and We have removed from you your cover, so your sight, this Day, is sharp."
وَقَالَ قَرِينُهُ هَٰذَا مَا لَدَيَّ عَتِيدٌ ﴿23﴾ أَلْقِيَا فِي جَهَنَّمَ كُلَّ كَفَّارٍ عَنِيدٍ ﴿24﴾
And his companion, [the angel], will say, "This [record] is what is with me, prepared."  [ Allah will say], "Throw into Hell every obstinate disbeliever,
مَنَّاعٍ لِلْخَيْرِ مُعْتَدٍ مُرِيبٍ ﴿25﴾ الَّذِي جَعَلَ مَعَ اللَّهِ إِلَٰهًا آخَرَ فَأَلْقِيَاهُ فِي الْعَذَابِ الشَّدِيدِ ﴿26﴾
Preventer of good, aggressor, and doubter, who made [as equal] with Allah another deity; then throw him into the severe punishment."
قَالَ قَرِينُهُ رَبَّنَا مَا أَطْغَيْتُهُ وَلَٰكِنْ كَانَ فِي ضَلَالٍ بَعِيدٍ ﴿27﴾
His [devil] companion will say, "Our Lord, I did not make him transgress, but he [himself] was in extreme error."
قَالَ لَا تَخْتَصِمُوا لَدَيَّ وَقَدْ قَدَّمْتُ إِلَيْكُمْ بِالْوَعِيدِ ﴿28﴾
[ Allah ] will say, "Do not dispute before Me, while I had already presented to you the warning.
مَا يُبَدَّلُ الْقَوْلُ لَدَيَّ وَمَا أَنَا بِظَلَّامٍ لِلْعَبِيدِ ﴿29﴾
The word will not be changed with Me, and never will I be unjust to the servants."
يَوْمَ نَقُولُ لِجَهَنَّمَ هَلِ امْتَلَأْتِ وَتَقُولُ هَلْ مِنْ مَزِيدٍ ﴿30﴾
On the Day We will say to Hell, "Have you been filled?" and it will say, "Are there some more,"
وَأُزْلِفَتِ الْجَنَّةُ لِلْمُتَّقِينَ غَيْرَ بَعِيدٍ ﴿31﴾
And Paradise will be brought near to the righteous, not far,
هَٰذَا مَا تُوعَدُونَ لِكُلِّ أَوَّابٍ حَفِيظٍ ﴿32﴾
[It will be said], "This is what you were promised - for every returner [to Allah ] and keeper [of His covenant]
مَنْ خَشِيَ الرَّحْمَٰنَ بِالْغَيْبِ وَجَاءَ بِقَلْبٍ مُنِيبٍ ﴿33﴾
Who feared the Most Merciful unseen and came with a heart returning [in repentance].
ادْخُلُوهَا بِسَلَامٍ ۖ ذَٰلِكَ يَوْمُ الْخُلُودِ ﴿34﴾ لَهُمْ مَا يَشَاءُونَ فِيهَا وَلَدَيْنَا مَزِيدٌ ﴿35﴾
Enter it in peace. This is the Day of Eternity." They will have whatever they wish therein, and with Us is more.
وَكَمْ أَهْلَكْنَا قَبْلَهُمْ مِنْ قَرْنٍ هُمْ أَشَدُّ مِنْهُمْ بَطْشًا فَنَقَّبُوا
And how many a generation before them did We destroy who were greater than them in [striking] power and had explored
فَنَقَّبُوا فِي الْبِلَادِ هَلْ مِنْ مَحِيصٍ ﴿36﴾
and had explored throughout the lands. Is there any place of escape?
إِنَّ فِي ذَٰلِكَ لَذِكْرَىٰ لِمَنْ كَانَ لَهُ قَلْبٌ أَوْ أَلْقَى السَّمْعَ وَهُوَ شَهِيدٌ ﴿37﴾
Indeed in that is a reminder for whoever has a heart or who listens while he is present [in mind].
وَلَقَدْ خَلَقْنَا السَّمَاوَاتِ وَالْأَرْضَ وَمَا بَيْنَهُمَا فِي سِتَّةِ أَيَّامٍ وَمَا مَسَّنَا مِنْ لُغُوبٍ ﴿38﴾
And We did certainly create the heavens and earth and what is between them in six days, and there touched Us no weariness.
فَاصْبِرْ عَلَىٰ مَا يَقُولُونَ وَسَبِّحْ بِحَمْدِ رَبِّكَ قَبْلَ طُلُوعِ الشَّمْسِ وَقَبْلَ الْغُرُوبِ ﴿39﴾
So be patient, [O Muhammad], over what they say and exalt [ Allah ] with praise of your Lord before the rising of the sun and before its setting,
وَمِنَ اللَّيْلِ فَسَبِّحْهُ وَأَدْبَارَ السُّجُودِ ﴿40﴾
And [in part] of the night exalt Him and after prostration.
وَاسْتَمِعْ يَوْمَ يُنَادِ الْمُنَادِ مِنْ مَكَانٍ قَرِيبٍ ﴿41﴾
And listen on the Day when the Caller will call out from a place that is near
يَوْمَ يَسْمَعُونَ الصَّيْحَةَ بِالْحَقِّ ۚ ذَٰلِكَ يَوْمُ الْخُرُوجِ ﴿42﴾
The Day they will hear the blast [of the Horn] in truth. That is the Day of Emergence [from the graves].
إِنَّا نَحْنُ نُحْيِي وَنُمِيتُ وَإِلَيْنَا الْمَصِيرُ ﴿43﴾
Indeed, it is We who give life and cause death, and to Us is the destination
يَوْمَ تَشَقَّقُ الْأَرْضُ عَنْهُمْ سِرَاعًا ۚ ذَٰلِكَ حَشْرٌ عَلَيْنَا يَسِيرٌ ﴿44﴾
On the Day the earth breaks away from them [and they emerge] rapidly; that is a gathering easy for Us.
نَحْنُ أَعْلَمُ بِمَا يَقُولُونَ ۖ وَمَا أَنْتَ عَلَيْهِمْ بِجَبَّارٍ ۖ فَذَكِّرْ بِالْقُرْآنِ مَنْ يَخَافُ وَعِيدِ ﴿45﴾
We are most knowing of what they say, and you are not over them a tyrant. But remind by the Qur'an whoever fears My threat.